Graf, Oskar Marie; Papers ger002
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria Graf, 1919-1967; 4; 378 file folders
  - Essays, stories, 1919-1978; 4.3
    - "Wie die Wilden 'Wilde' wurden. Eine Sinngeschichte aus der Kolonialzeit", 1967; typescript, clipping (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 113)
    - "How 'the Savages' Became Savage" ("Wie die Wilden 'Wilde' wurden", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 114)
    - "Wie ich Ritter Possart zum Laufen brachte" / "Ernst Ritter von Possart", 1963; typescript, clipping (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 115)
    - "Wie unsre Thekla das Mitleid verlor...", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 116)
    - "Die Wimmerl", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 117)
    - "Wo ist euer Häuschen?", 1977; clipping (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 118)
    - "Wollgramm. Eine Legende", 1963; typescript, clippings (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 119)
    - "Der Wopfner-Wiggl irritiert sich. Eine altbairische Schnurre von früherszeiten", 1979; typescript, clippings (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 120)
    - "Die wunderbare Tat des Beatus Null. (Eine Geschichte, die wahr sein könnte)", 1978; clipping (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 121)
    - "Der zerstörte Schiller", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 122)
    - "Das Zimmer des Erhängten", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 123)
    - "Zwei Geschichten von Zar Iwan dem Schrecklichen" / "Iwan der Schreckliche liebreich und gut", 1932; typescripts, clippings (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 124)
    - "Ivan, Czar by the Grace of God. Two Legends" ("Zwei Geschichte von Zar Iwan dem Schrecklichen"), Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 125)
    - "Die Zwillinge", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 126)
  - English stories, essays, Undated; 4.4
    - "Far too lucky!", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 127)
    - "German Writers in America", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 128)
    - "The Guest of Honor", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 129)
    - "Heritage". Translated by Richard Winston, Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 130)
    - "In a little Polish Village. A World War Recollection", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 131)
    - "The Law and the Lady-Photographer", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 132)
    - "Liz Keeps Her Nerve. Short Story", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 133)
    - "Midnight Ghost in Greenwich Village" / "Greenwich Village Spook" (translated by Sophie Prombaum, Undated; typescripts (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 134)
    - "Old Jeromir tells a tale", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 135)
    - "Pet and Baby. A Story", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 136)
    - "What's That to Us?", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 137)
  - Miscellaneous writings, Undated; 4.5
    - Aphorisms, Undated; clippings, photocopies of typescripts (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 138)
    - Poems, in German, Undated; typescripts, clippings (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 139)
    - Poem. Dutch translation, Undated; clipping (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 140)
    - Poems. English translations, Undated; typescripts (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 141)
    - Radio play: "Humor der deutschen Landschaften (Bayern)", Undated; mimeographed (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 142)
    - Speech texts, Undated; typescripts (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 143)
    - Untitled critiques of other writers, personalities, Undated; photocopies of typescripts (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 144)
    - Fragments and untitled pieces, Undated; typescripts and photocopies (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 145)
    - Loose typescript pages, corrections, Undated (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 146)
    - Handwritten notes, note cards, Undated (Box 7 (4-Published and unpublished writings of Oskar Maria ), Folder 147)
- Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria Graf, 1920-1990; 5; 52 file folders
  This series consists primarily of clippings of articles about Graf over eight decades, including general articles, as well as numerous commemorative articles on birthdays and anniversaries of his death. Also included are typescripts of a number of articles discussing Graf and his works.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Adaptations of Graf's work, 5.1
    - Bernfeld, Siegfried. "Shadows of Fear", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 147)
    - Bierbichler, Josef. "Triumph der Gerechten", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 148)
    - Kursawe, Thomas. Play adaptation of a Graf novel, Undated (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 149)
    - Film adaptations, Undated (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 150)
  - Secondary materials about Graf, 5.2
    - Articles about Graf, anonymous typescripts, Undated (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 151)
    - Articles about Graf from books, periodicals, primarily photocopies, Undated (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 152)
    - Amery, Carl. "Zum Problem Oskar Maria Graf", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 153)
    - Dollinger, Hans. "Oskar Maria Graf, ein Dichter und Rebell aus Bayern", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 154)
    - George, Manfred. "Deutsche Schriftsteller in U.S.A. Das Schicksal einer literarischen Emigration", Undated; typescript, photocopy (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 155)
    - Graf, Gisela. Untitled typescripts on Graf, Undated (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 156)
    - Kaufmann, Ulrich. Articles in books, periodicals, Undated (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 157)
    - Petersen, Harold. "Ein deutscher Dichter in der Diaspora", Undated; typescript (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 158)
    - Pfanner, Helmut, Undated (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 159)
      Typescripts of articles about Graf.
    - Pfanner, Helmut. Graf articles in books, periodicals, Undated (Box 7 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 160)
    - Schaber, Will. "Interview mit Oskar Maria Graf (ca. 1961, New York)", Undated; typescript (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 1)
    - Stadler, Ulrich. "Oskar Maria Graf. Zur Eröffnung der Wanderausstellung in Basel am 23.4.1979", Undated; typescript (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 2)
    - Teclaw, Richard. "Ein Heimatdichter im Exil", Undated; typescript (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 3)
    - Announcements of lectures on Graf, readings from his works, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 4)
    - Texts of radio discussions about Graf, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 5)
    - Texts of radio discussions about Graf's works, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 6)
    - Encyclopedia, lexicon articles, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 7)
    - Articles about Graf, other languages, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 8)
    - General articles about Graf, 1920s; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 9)
    - General articles about Graf, 1930s; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 10)
    - General articles about Graf, 1940s; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 11)
    - Articles on the occasion of Graf's 50th birthday, 1944; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 12)
    - General articles about Graf, 1950s; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 13)
    - Articles on the occasion of Graf's 60th birthday, 1954; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 14)
    - Articles on the occasion of Graf's 65th birthday, 1959; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 15)
    - General articles about Graf, 1960s; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 16)
    - Articles on the occasion of Graf's 70th birthday, 1964; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 17)
    - Obituaries, 1967; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 18)
    - Articles on the occasion of Graf's 75th birthday, 1969; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 19)
    - General articles about Graf, 1970s; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 20)
    - Articles commemorating the 5th anniversary of Graf's death, 1972; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 21)
    - Articles on the occasion of Graf's 80th birthday, 1974; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 22)
    - Articles on the formation of the Oskar Maria Graf Society, 1974 (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 23)
    - Articles commemorating the 10th anniversary of Graf's death, 1977; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 24)
    - Articles on the occasion of Graf's 85th birthday, 1979; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 25)
    - General articles about Graf, 1980s; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 26)
    - Articles commemorating the 15th anniversary of Graf's death, 1982; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 27)
    - Articles on the occasion of Graf's 90th birthday, 1984; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 28)
    - Articles commemorating the 20th anniversary of Graf's death, 1987; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 29)
    - General articles about Graf, 1990s; clippings (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 30)
    - Beschreibung eines Volksschriftstellers, 1975 (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 31)
      Reviews of Graf's posthumously published work.
    - Oskar Maria Graf in seinen Briefen, 1984 (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 32)
      Reviews of published letters.
    - General reviews of Graf's writing, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 33)
    - Short critiques of Graf's works for book jackets, etc., Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 34)
    - Book jackets, illustrations for books, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 35)
    - Publisher's advertisements of Graf's books, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 36)
    - Reviews of books about Graf, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 37)
    - Articles about Gisela Graf, Undated (Box 8 (5-Adaptations, secondary materials about Oskar Maria), Folder 38)
- Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions, 1972-1988; 6; 30 file folders
  This series consists of materials pertaining to exhibits of Graf and his work, and includes materials from the exhibits themselves, as well as notes and ideas by Gisela Graf in her efforts to assist with the exhibitions.
  - Lists of exhibits, notes, Undated (Box 8 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 39)
  - Placards from exhibitions, Undated (Box 8 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous notes by Gisela Graf, primarily pertaining to exhibit details and preparations, Undated (Box 8 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 41)
  - Exhibit at Brandeis University, 1972 April 21-1972 May 19 (Box 8 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 42)
  - Exhibit at University of New Hampshire, 1974 July 22-1974 August 22 (Box 8 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 43)
  - "One Man Show", 1977 (Box 8 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 44)
  - Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich, 1977 August 8-1977 September 4 (Box 8 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 45)
  - Die Deutsche Bibliothek, Frankfurt am Main, Germany, 1977 December (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 1)
  - Heilbronner Stadtbücherei, Heilbronn, Germany, 1978 March 1-1978 March 31 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 2)
  - Wiener Museum des 20. Jahrhunderts, Vienna, Austria, 1978 September 6-1978 October 15 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 3)
  - Mattersburg, 1978 November 22 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 4)
  - Heinrich-Heine-Institut, Düsseldorf, Germany, 1979 January 12-1979 March 4 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 5)
  - Universitätsbibliothek, Basel, Switzerland, 1979 April 23-1979 May 19 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 6)
  - Akademie der Künste, Berlin, 1979 September 7-1979 September 30 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 7)
  - Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Munich, 1979 October 22-1979 October 31 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 8)
  - Universitätsbibliothek, Münster, Germany, 1980 February (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 9)
  - California State University, Long Beach, 1980 February 28-1980 March 15 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 10)
  - Universitäts- und Stadtbibliothek, Cologne, Germany, 1980 October 1-1980 November 8 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 11)
  - Bremer Universitätsbibliothek, 1980 December (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 12)
  - Musil-Haus, Klagenfurt, Germany, 1981 February 2-1981 February 28 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 13)
  - Universitätsbibliothek, Eichstätt, Germany, 1981 May (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 14)
  - Stadtbibliothek, Ulm, Germany, 1982 March 1-1982 March 20 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 15)
  - Kreisbibliothek, Kronach, 1982 October 1-1982 November 19 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 16)
  - Staatsbibliothek, Hamburg, Germany, 1983 February-1983 March 12 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 17)
  - Goethe Institute, London, 1983 May 5 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 18)
  - Theresien-Gymnasium, Munich, 1983 July (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 19)
  - Wilhelmspalais, Stuttgart, Germany, 1983 September 5-1983 October 2 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 20)
  - Graf / Feuchwanger exhibit, Munich, Germany, 1984 July 2-1984 July 22 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 21)
  - Braunschweig, Germany, 1988 November 1-1988 December 17 (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 22)
  - Exhibits, general, Undated (Box 9 (6-Oskar Maria Graf Exhibitions), Folder 23)
- Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics, 7; 9 file folders
  This series contains materials pertaining to the organizations in which Graf was involved, primarily during his years in the United States.
  - Deutscher Arbeiter Club, Inc., Undated (Box 9 (7-Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics), Folder 24)
  - German-American Writer's Association (G.A.W.A.)., Undated (Box 9 (7-Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics), Folder 25)
  - P.E.N. Club, Undated (Box 9 (7-Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics), Folder 26)
  - International P.E.N., Undated (Box 9 (7-Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics), Folder 27)
  - Schutzverband deutscher Schriftsteller (SDS), Undated (Box 9 (7-Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics), Folder 28)
  - Graf "Stammtisch", New York, Undated (Box 9 (7-Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics), Folder 29)
  - Verband deutscher Schriftsteller (VS), Undated (Box 9 (7-Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics), Folder 30)
  - Copyright materials, Undated (Box 9 (7-Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics), Folder 31)
  - Exile research, Undated (Box 9 (7-Miscellaneous materials on organizations, topics), Folder 32)
- Photographs and drawings, 1911-1984; 8; 24 file folders
  This series contains hundreds of photographs, drawings and reproductions of paintings, which document all aspects of Graf's life, his family, his colleagues and friends, and exhibitions of his works.
  - Portrait photos of Oskar Maria Graf, 1911-1955 (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 33)
  - Portrait photos of Oskar Maria Graf, 1960s (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 34)
  - Snapshot photos of Graf, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 35)
  - Photographs of Graf and family members, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 36)
  - Oskar Maria Graf with second wife, Mirjam, 1930s-1940s (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 37)
  - Oskar Maria Graf with third wife, Gisela, 1961-1977 (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 38)
  - Photos of Graf with others (8" × 10"). Oversize photos (2) stored with German Émigré Photograph Collection, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 39)
  - Photos of Graf with others, snapshots, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 40)
  - Photos of others (friends and historical figures), identified, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 41)
  - Photos of others, unidentified, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 42)
  - Photos of Graf's home, bust, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 43)
  - Snapshots of Berg, Graf's place of birth, and Aufkirchen, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 44)
  - Photos of Graf's gravesite, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 45)
  - Stammtisch photos, ca. 1964-1965 (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 46)
  - Vacation photos, 1950s-1960s (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 47)
  - Gisela Blauner Graf, alone and with others, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 48)
  - Historical photographs, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 49)
  - Photographs from Oskar Maria Graf exhibits, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 50)
  - Negatives, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 51)
  - Photos reproduced in newspapers, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 52)
  - Graf caricature by B.F. Dolbin, Undated (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 53)
  - Political cartoon featuring Graf, 1943 December 6 (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 54)
  - Reproductions of Georg Schrimpf oil painting of Graf, 1918 (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 55)
  - Sketch of Graf by L. Matulay, dated 1952 (Box 9 (8-Photographs and drawings), Folder 56)
  - Oversized materials -- Photographs, Undated (Box 10 (8-Photographs and drawings))